Guide to the Nycum Family Papers, 1825-1912 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Nycum Family papers 1825-1912 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Nycum Family
12.1 Linear Feet 9,057 Items
Family from Ray's Hill, Bedford County, Pennsylvania.
Papers of John Nycum and John Q. Nycum include the letters of Philip Weisel concerning family matters and the sale of mineral water, and the correspondence and papers of several members of the Nycum family concerning the management of general merchandise businesses; business conditions; family matters; and the Civil War, including descriptions of camp life in Pennsylvania and Louisiana and the Confederate raid on Chambersburg, Pennsylvania, 1864. The collection also contains bills, receipts, legal papers, and miscellaneous items, including advertisements, circulars, political material, and reports, 1850-1856, of several teachers in Bedford County, Pennsylvania, listing pupils and their records. Volumes include mercantile daybooks and memorandum books of John Nycum, Simon Nycum, and Philip Weisel; record books of the Evangelical Lutheran Church of Ray's Hill, Pennsylvania; account books of public schools of Bedford County; and a mercantile ledger of D. Eshleman and Company.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Nycum Family Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 1947-1948.
Collection Overview
Papers of John Nycum and John Q. Nycum include the letters of Philip Weisel concerning family matters and the sale of mineral water, and the correspondence and papers of several members of the Nycum family concerning the management of general merchandise businesses; business conditions; family matters; and the Civil War, including descriptions of camp life in Pennsylvania and Louisiana and the Confederate raid on Chambersburg, Pennsylvania, 1864. The collection also contains bills, receipts, legal papers, and miscellaneous items, including advertisements, circulars, political material, and reports, 1850-1856, of several teachers in Bedford County, Pennsylvania, listing pupils and their records. Volumes include mercantile daybooks and memorandum books of John Nycum, Simon Nycum, and Philip Weisel; record books of the Evangelical Lutheran Church of Ray's Hill, Pennsylvania; account books of public schools of Bedford County; and a mercantile ledger of D. Eshleman and Company.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
General stores -- Pennsylvania -- Ray’s Hill
Merchants -- Pennsylvania -- Ray’s Hill
Mineral waters
Soldiers -- United States -- Correspondence
Tanning
Teachers -- Pennsylvania -- Bedford County
Pennsylvania -- Commerce
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence and Legal Papers Series, 1825-1900 and undated, (2 boxes)
  - 1825-1870 (Box 1)
  - 1871-1900 and undated (Box 2)
- Financial Papers Series, 1840-1912, (15 boxes)
  - 1840-1845 (Box 3)
  - 1846-1853 (Box 4)
  - 1854-1860 (Box 5)
  - 1861-1864 June (Box 6)
  - 1864 July-1872 (Box 7)
  - 1873-1877 (Box 8)
  - 1878-1881 June (Box 9)
  - 1881 July-1883 Oct. (Box 10)
  - 1883 Nov.-1884 Dec. (Box 11)
  - 1885-1886 Oct. (Box 12)
  - 1886 Nov.-1888 Dec. (Box 13)
  - 1889-1890 (Box 14)
  - 1891-1893 (Box 15)
  - 1894-1897 June (Box 16)
  - 1897 July-1912 (Box 17)
- Volumes, (2 boxes)
  - Volumes (Box 17-18)